Inventory of the William Short Papers 1772-1931
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
William Short Papers, [1772], 1789-1847, 1931.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. 39.2 Sh9
20 items.
Letters, 1789, 1839, and 1846-1847, of William Short, while a diplomat in France, and later while living in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.
Short family,; Alexandrine de Rohan-Chabot, duchesse de la Rochefoucauld,; William Short,; George Washington.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 1 item, n.d.
Gift: 1 item, 07/26/1934.
Gift: 6 items, 1938.
Gift: 1 item, 04/15/1942.
Gift 1 item, 04/30/1945.
Gift: 1 item, 01/1967.
Acc. No. 82-6; Gift: 5 items, 01/1982.
Acc. No. 1995.33; Purchase: 1 item, 06/16/1995.
Biographical/Historical Information
William Short was born in Surry County, Virginia, in 1759, the son of William Short and Elizabeth (Skipwith) Short. He graduated in 1779 from the College of William and Mary where he had been one of the founders of Phi Beta Kappa. He acted as Thomas Jefferson's private secretary in Paris and as secretary of legation and charge d'affairs. He was minister to The Hague. He participated in negotiations of the Pinchney Treaty with Spain. Short died in 1849.
Scope and Content Information
Letters, [1772], 1789, 1839, and 1846-1847, of William Short, while a diplomat in France, and later while living in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, with the later letters discussing the settlement of his estate with his nephew, Charles W. Short (1794-1863), of Louisville, Kentucky. Also includes copies of Short's appointment to various diplomatic posts, 1790-1794; a copy of George Washington's letter to the King of Spain explaining Short's departure from Spain, 1796; his will; a genealogical chart of the Short family; an article of his love affair with the Duchess de la Rochefoucauld; and his watch and fob.
Arrangement
Organization
This collection is organized into 5 series. Series 1 contains correspondence; Series 2 contains manuscript volumes; Series 3 contains photographs; Series 4 contain artifacts; and Series 5 conatins miscellaneous.
Arrangement
Series 1 is arranged chronologically.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Diplomats -- United States -- Correspondence.
Persons:
Rochefoucauld, Alexandrine de Roahn-Chabot, duchesse de la, d. 1839.; Short, William, 1759- 1849.; Washington, George, 1732-1799.
Family name:
Short family.
Contents List
  Series 1: Correspondence
- Correspondence, 1789-1847. (Folder 1)
  Arranged chronologically.
  - William Short, Paris, [France], to [?] Donald, n.p., 8 October 1789., 1 page. ALS. Including typescript. (Folder 1)
    Mentions that [Thomas] Jefferson is at Havre; trusts his opinion of whether the warrants should be sold at a loss to purchase certificates by January 1; mentions that the market will probably be good for wheat and flour.
  - Commission signed by President George Washington and Thomas Jefferson, New York, [New York], appointing William Short Charge des Affaires for the United States to France, 20 April 1790., 1 page. Pst. of DS. (Folder 1)
  - Commission signed by Alexander Hamilton, Secretary of the Treasury, authorizing William Short to borrow money to finance the public and foreign debt of the United States, 1 September 1790., 2 pages. Pst of DS. (Folder Medium oversize file)
  - Certificate of appointment of William Carmichael and William Short as commissioners plenpotentiary from the United States to the King of Spain, 18 March 1792., 1 page. CY of DS; Signed by George Washington and Thomas Jefferson, with the Seal of the United States affixed. (Folder Medium oversize file)
  - French passport issued to William Short as Minister to France, 29 December 1792., 1 page. Pst of DS. (Folder 1)
  - Appointment, signed by President George Washington and Edmund Randolph, of William Short, giving him the authority to negotiate with the King of Spain concerning the navigation of the Mississippi River, 11 July 1794., 1 page. Pst of DS. (Folder Medium oversize file)
  - George Washington, President [of the United States], to "Our Great and Good Friend His Catholic Majesty," [Charles IV, King of Spain], n.p., 11 June 1796., 1 page. Cy of LS (Folder 1)
    Explains the departure of William Short, Minister, being due to ill health. [Accession information states that this letter was William Short's personal copy].
  - William Short, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania] to Henry Dilworth Gilpin, n.p., 15 May 1839., 2 pages. ALS. (Folder 1)
    Recommending a young man for a position at the Philadelphia Navy Yard.
  - William Short, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Charles W. Short, Louisville, Kentucky, 14 November 1846., 2 pages. ALS. (Folder 1)
    Mentions his failing health; gives his opinion of Charles' son's marriage; states the last letter received was accompanied by the deed.
  - William Short, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Charles W. Short, Louisville, Kentucky, 20 March 1847., 8 pages. ALS. (Folder 1)
    Mentions defeating the descendents of William Penn; asks that Charles make sure that his favorite sister, Martha, is provided for; states he has made a deed naming Charles heir to his house. (4 pp., ALS.) Including postscript from W[illiam] Short, Philad[elphi]a, [Pennsylvania], to Charles W. Short, Louisville, Kentucky, 21 March [1847], concerning revision of the deed to his house, future care of his eldest sister martha and other Financial information. (4 pages. ALS)
  - William Short, n.p., to Charles W. Short, Louisville, Kentucky. 29 March 1847., 3 pages. ALS. (Folder 1)
    Expresses his opinion concerning wills and his desires concerning the handling of his personal will. (2 pages. ALS.) Including postscript, from William Short, n.p., to Charles W. Short, Louisville, Kentucky, 30 March [1847], concerning relatives previously left out of his will that he wishes to include. (1 page.)
  - Will of William Short, 11 September 1847., 5 pages. ADS. Certified copy attached. (Folder 1)
  - William Short, n.p., to P.S. DuPonceau, n.p., n.d., 1 page. ALS. (Folder 1)
    Mentions his indisposition, and the reception of "our friend" into "our Society," his apprehension over the condition of Mde. G., and his hope to see him in the course of the day. (Accession 1995.33)
  Series 2: Manuscript volumes
- Manuscript volumes, [1772]. (Folder 1)
  - Book of Robert Munford containing rules for calculating currency discounts, including the name William Short, [1772]., 1 volume, 86 pages. (Folder 1)
  Series 3: Photographs
- Photographs, [November 1983], n.d. (Folder 1)
  - Photograph, of the watch and fob once owned by William Short. [3 November 1983]., 1 item. P1. Photograph. Black and White. No negative available. 8"x10" (Folder 1)
    Including documentation, 3 November 1983, by the National Museum of American History, giving a detailed analysis of the watch. (1 page.)
  - Photograph of "Rosalie," the Duchess de la Rouchefoucauld, n.d., 1 item. P2. Photograph. Color. Oval cut mounted on 3 1/2" x 4 1/2" mat. (Folder 1)
    Including documentation of the photograph. (4 pages.)
    Also inluding an article entitled Our First Career Diplomat and the Duchesse or Uncle Willie's Wallet and the Lady Inside, by Lucille McWane Watson. (18 pages.)
  Series 4: Artifacts
- Artifacts, n.d. (Folder Artifact file)
  - Watch and fob owned and worn by William Short, n.d., 2 items. A1. (Folder Artifact file)
  Series 5: Miscellaneous
- Miscellaneous, 1931. (Folder Oversize file)
  - Genealogical chart of descendents of William Short, compiled by William Allen Richardson, 1931., 1 blue print. (Folder Oversize file.)